This is the Vancouver Seaw Wall, a 28 km
bikeway that's so long it's actually
considered the world's longest
continuous waterfront bike path. It's a
bit of a niche title, but 28 straight
kilm of bikeway is still really
impressive and even more impressive when
you consider that lots of cities have
parts of their waterfronts that look
like this or or even this. I happened to
be in Vancouver this past June and when
I heard about the Seaw wall, I knew that
I wanted to check it out. Actually, I
wanted to do more than that. I wanted to
ride all 28 km from the Vancouver
Convention Center downtown all the way
out to Spanish Banks Park on the
doorstep of the UBC campus. Would I make
it all in one go or my feeble legs give
out? And will I reach an epiphany about
the merits of long-distance bicycle
paths? Well, there's only one way to
find out. Let's ride the Vancouver Seaw
Wall after the bike bell.
First things first, I need a bike. I
rented one from Spokes Bicycle Rental. I
picked it up because it was close to the
start of the seaw wall, but I just want
to give them a quick review.
Professional staff, quality bikes, fast
service, easiest rental I've ever done.
Here's my trusty bike. I got an ebike,
but I could only put it on the absolute
lowest setting because otherwise I
wouldn't have the range to get it back.
That's a little foreshadowing for you.
Now that I have a bike, I need a map.
Here's where I'm going. As far as I
know, there's no official map of the
Seaw Wall bike path. I've heard it
starts at Crab Park, but I've also heard
it starts at the convention center.
After some on-site reconnaissance, I
think the convention center is the right
starting point. Anyway, the path moves
from the convention center through Cole
Harbor, then enters iconic Stanley Park.
It's larger than New York City Central
Park and feels wilder. It's like a
little slice of West Coast nature in the
city. After the seaw wall wraps around
Stanley Park, it continues through the
West End, then into the Falls Creek
area. After pulling that loop, it heads
through the Kitalano neighborhood before
getting into Spanish Banks Park way over
near the University of British Columbia.
Okay, I have my bike. I got my route.
So, let's throw it back to Pass Me to
get this trip started. All right, I'm
here at the beginning of Vancouver's
Seaw Wall. I'm ready to ride all 28
kilometers. Got my helmet, got my bike
here at the beginning. Let's see how
this goes. I'm excited to give it a
shot. The path starts out feeling very
urban with storefronts opening out onto
the waterfront and the path itself. On
the water side, I was shocked by how
many sea planes took off and landed
right near Cole Harbor. Felt like it own
little airport on the water. As I was
cycling, I started thinking about the
journey. I'm an avid bicycle commuter,
but my commute is about 5 or 6 km long.
Most bicycle trips are less than 5 km
long, though there's an increased
interest in longer distance bicycle
commuting, particularly as ebikes have
made it easier on the legs to travel
farther. The limiting factor these days,
as I see it, are the lack of networks of
long-distance bicycle paths separated
from traffic, making the commute
stress-free. I know I'm not the kind of
person who feels comfortable riding
along the side of a rural road or
highway, and I know that I'm in the
majority. In some ways, this trip is a
test of my intuition. If the seaw wall
can keep me safe and comfortable for 28
km, I'd be right. The limiting factor is
the infrastructure, not the
transportation mode. Anyway, I made my
way through this area fairly quickly,
and pretty soon I was encountering
wildlife and green spaces, which means I
was at Stanley Park's doorstep. I
stopped to take some video of this flock
of Canada geese in Deonian Harbor Park.
Look how cute the gosslings were. Well,
I must have done something wrong because
this goose started staring me down.
After that moment, I firmly believe that
the geese along my route had it in for
me. I didn't know it yet, but this was
far from the last goose I would see.
Now, before I move on to Stanley Park,
let pass me reflect on the Coal Harbor
part of the trip. All right, so I'm
officially out of the downtown Cole
Harbor area and I'm entering Stanley
Park and so far so good. Uh it's a
really nice continuous quiet path. No
interaction with cars. The only quibbles
are that sometimes you could see that
the path was completed I think with
different projects as the part of Pull
Harbor is being developed. So, the
signage between those areas sometimes
got a little bit tricky, but obviously I
got here just fine. So, uh, no big deal.
Been so far so fun and I'm really
excited to go into Stanley Park next and
see what that part of the path has to
offer. Like I said, those geese guard
the entrance to Stanley Park, a major
phase of this 28 km ride. Now, an actual
commuter would not follow the seaw wall
like I'm starting to do here. They would
just cut across the southern edge of the
park, which comes complete with its own
bike paths. You can save a lot of time
that way. But I've never taken a long
recreational ride completely free from
cars, so I was eager to get a taste of
it on this section of the route. Now,
pretty quickly, I came upon an
information booth near the path. I
believe it's more oriented to the
parking lot, but I appreciated that was
visible and accessible from the path.
There were actually a couple of other
rest stops on the first part of this
trip. Cyclist can stop at the totem
poles for a bathroom break and pick up
some souvenirs for the trip. There was a
tour guide explaining the significance
of the totem poles to a group there, but
I didn't catch it. I had a lot of ground
to cover, so I moved on. In this section
of the path, I seem to stop every couple
of minutes to film some beautiful view
of the harbor or some landmark like this
really nice little lighthouse. There was
yet another rest stop not too far up the
path, less than a kilometer from the
totem poles. This was the Lumberman's
Arch Concession booth. It was closed
when I was there, though. From there,
the path starts to feel more remote and
natural, which I have mixed feelings
about. I really love the idea of having
lots of places to stop along this path.
I have kids. If I was going to take them
on this path when they were younger, it
would be nice to know that I'm no more
than a kilometer or two from a snack in
a bathroom. It's also kind of fun
stopping at these outposts and seeing
other cyclists enjoying the same
activity as me. I don't know, it's kind
of like gas stations for bikes. Gas
stations for cars smell bad and are gray
and gross, but the totem pole stop was
delightful. That said, I could really
lose myself on this part of the trip
just soaking in the views as I made my
way towards the Lion's Gate Bridge at
the northernmost point on my ride. I'd
stop every couple minutes to take shots
of the view. After more sightseeing, I
rounded the corner of Prospect Point and
its lighthouse in the Lionsgate Bridge
and stopped for another moment of
reflection. I now officially rounded the
corner and I passed the northernmost
part of Stanley Park. And I got to say
this is a pretty nice path. Um I'm I
think I'm on some of the oldest parts of
the path here because it's kind of got
that old stone and it gets pretty
narrow. I can see why they made it one
way uh for a lot of this for cyclists
because uh there were some parts where
we even had to get dismount and walk
with pedestrians. Uh, and they're doing
some, uh, construction work back there.
We had to dismount a couple other times
as well, so pretty narrow. Uh, I would
have loved for this to be like maybe
twice as wide. Uh, but it makes you go
at kind of a leisurely pace, which makes
a lot of sense considering this is a
recreational trail uh, along a park, but
all in all, great ride so far, and I'm
excited to keep going. The path up until
this point was definitely narrow, and
this had to do with the history of the
seaw wall. The project began all the way
back in 1917, and the final segment in
San Park wasn't completed until 1980.
Back then, Vancouver wasn't the large
city it is today. And back in 1917,
cycling was popular, but probably not
something you consider dedicating
additional width to on the path. To
solve this traffic problem, the Stanley
Park segment of the Seaw Wall path was
made one way in 1984. I believe you can
go the other direction on a bike, just
not right along the seaw wall. The city
has continued to extend the path along
the waterfront through the Falls Creek
neighborhood and out as far as Spanish
Banks Park. There's some conflicting
information on the city's website about
how long the seaw wall actually is and
where it officially ends. It says 28 km
on the website ending at Spanish Banks
Park, but this map from the website says
it's 22 km, but it also continues onto
the University of British Columbia. Now,
I can tell you from my own measurements
that it's 28 km to Spanish Banks Park,
and the bike path does indeed end there.
It should continue onto the campus for
UBC, though. If it did, you could have a
continuous path almost all the way from
the convention center to the airport. As
I continue on to the west side of
Stanley Park, we start getting to some
beaches. Even with the beaches, this
side of the park and the path itself
feels wilder than the eastern side. It's
kind of hard to believe that I'm
technically in the city limits of
Vancouver. But all too soon, I start to
reach civilization again, and I run into
some confusing signage. I actually end
up taking the wrong turn and started
heading back toward Cole Harbor. Now,
some of this might have been because I
was trying to bike and film in a city
I'm just visiting, but a few times in
this ride, I got a little concerned that
I wasn't actually in the right place,
like actually on the Seaw wall path.
We'll come back to this topic later. Uh,
just like I eventually came back to this
right path. Now, as I exited the park, I
found myself back in the midst of
highdensity urban life. As much as I
like Stanley Park, I was happy to be
back in the hustle and bustle,
especially on this incredibly wide,
comfortable curb protected cycle track.
I'll let past me discuss my initial
observations with this area. Okay, so
I'm out of Stanley Park. I'm just about
to get into uh the False Creek area.
Before I do that, I wanted to talk about
the stretch I just was on, which might
be my favorite part of the path so far.
Uh after you get out of the park, it
seems like they just decided to close
half the roadway that went along the the
harbor here and turn it into a two-way
cycle track. And it's really been
amazing. It's wide, comfortable. Uh
again, probably my favorite part. The
only downside is that uh it seems like
they did that in part to uh give more
space to pedestrians down right up
against the water. So right here you're
not like right shoulderto-shoulder with
the waterfront uh but you're up on the
street level a little bit. So it's a
little bit of a downside, but all in
all, it's a really comfortable ride. Um
the other thing I would note is that at
this point um you don't see a lot of
like sort of seaw wall branding or
signage. It really does just feel like
you're on a cycle track, part of the
larger cycle track network in sort of
greater downtown Vancouver. Um, so just
interesting observation there, but I'm
excited to get into the False Creek
area. It's really uh cool and beautiful.
So, let's do that next. False Creek is a
fascinating neighborhood. Historically,
it was the industrial heart of central
Vancouver, but after Expo 86, the entire
area began a process of redevelopment.
North False Creek, where I'm recycling
now, redeveloped first, and it
redeveloped into housing at roughly 100
homes per acre in these iconic Vancouver
point towers. The result is an area that
feels like a city, but also kind of
feels like the suburbs with kids,
families, people walking dogs, parks,
elementary schools, and an overall quiet
vibe. Perhaps these geese were enforcing
the piece here, as they seem to reside
in every park in North Falls Creek. I
kept my distance just in case. I love
the paths along this section of the
route as they're some of the best
overall. They separate out cyclists and
pedestrians and have lots of signage to
make that clear. The paths are wider
than they were in Stanley Park, but
right up against the water, something
that wasn't true in the neighborhood
just before False Creek. For my money,
these might be the best bike paths in
North America, but feel free to nominate
others in the comments. As I continued
along North False Creek, I was excited
to reach Science World at the far
eastern end, but ran into an issue. a
massive flock of geese right up along
the path and I actually had to stop and
dismount it to avoid hitting a few who
had clearly set up some sort of
makeshift checkpoint. After a close
encounter by one I can only assume was
the ring leader, they let me pass
without incident. I can't be sure, but I
feel like while I passed by unscathed,
they must have done something to my
GoPro because it stopped recording and I
got no footage of me passing by Science
World. I parked my bike and found that
the battery had inexplicably died.
Luckily, I had a backup camera and a
portable battery to charge it up so I
could use it later in the trip. It
looked like there's some construction
happening just south of Science World
interrupting the very nice path. And
again, I couldn't help but wonder if the
geese had something to do with it. After
regrouping, I started traveling along
South Falls Creek, home to the former
Olympic Village for the 2010 Winter
Games. This part of the path has a lot
less density than the northern part,
making it feel even more suburban. The
housing is really different, has a lot
more variety than North Falls Creek, and
it made it really fun to bike through
and kind of check out all those places.
But I'll let pass me describe this part
of the route. So, at this point, I'm
already on the south side of False
Creek. And, you know, it's been pretty
residential, quite honestly. Uh, it's
interesting how the path has changed.
The seaw wall has changed as I've gone
through phase by phase, but right now
it's very residential, very quiet,
people walking their dogs. Um, another
thing to add at this point on the trip,
I don't know how many kilometers in I
am. I'll put it on screen somewhere. But
it's definitely starting to feel like a
long bike ride. I'm I'm on an ebike, so
it doesn't feel bad on the legs, but
honestly, the butt's getting a little
sore. I'm not used to being on a bike
for this long. But, uh, all in all,
still really fun. Uh, really enjoyable.
Um, and we'll see what happens in the
next phase after False Creek. Uh, this
is an area of Vancouver I've never
really been to before. So, excited to
check it out, but a little bit unsure
about what's coming next. So, we'll see.
The next phase of the path is the one I
guess I would call Kitalano. It's the
part of the route from Granville Island
all the way through Kitalano Park and
the Yacht Club. This area feels
completely different than Falls Creek
and really every phase of the journey
before it immediately begins with
something shocking, an interaction with
cars. As far as I can remember, this is
the first time when I really actually
had to cross a street with cars on it,
and it was honestly kind of jarring. I
had gotten used to not even thinking
about cars, and I almost forgot to stop
and look both ways. Soon after that, the
comfortable bike paths of False Creek
gave way to some more awkward path
routes and eventually this kind of
confusing area with bike lanes and a
parking lot. This again was one of the
first areas where bikes felt more like
an afterthought instead of the top
priority. It was also again where I
didn't know exactly where I was going or
if I was going the right direction.
There were some seaw wall signs that
gave me enough confidence to believe
that I was indeed on the right track. As
an aside, I really wanted to test the
signage and path consistency on this
trip, so I hardly ever checked my phone
for directions. I really only checked to
see how far I had to go, and as a
result, sometimes I took suboptimal
routes when things weren't clear, but
that's okay. After the parking lot, I
entered this park with gravel pathways
shared by cyclists and pedestrians. I
don't know about you, but I don't really
like riding on gravel with a normal city
bike. After the perfect paths of False
Creek, this honestly felt pretty bad. I
did take the opportunity to sit on a
bench and enjoy the view, so I made the
best of it. It didn't get better
immediately because either I missed a
sign again or just went the wrong way.
But I ended up pushing my bike over a
grassy lawn to find my way back to the
seaw wall path, which at this point was
again a cycle track along a roadway. No
surprise that my least favorite part of
the seaw wall was inhabited by geese,
who again performed another checkpoint,
no doubt privately laughing at my
navigation skills. After riding in the
cycle track for a bit, this path led me
back onto the paths of Kitalano Beach
Park, which based on my brief ride
through it seemed quite nice. This
neighborhood has that high density that
feels lower density vibe that I always
really enjoy. And I was in good spirits
as I exited the park and entered a
segment of the route I like to call
Point Grey Road. Here's Point Grey Road
on a map. You can see that it's a
builtup area between Kitalano Beach Park
and Jericho Beach Park. And there is no
seaw wall to ride along here, just fancy
houses with great views of English Bay.
This is one of the last segments of the
Seaw wall path to be completed. And it
feels like a compromise. There's nothing
wrong with compromise, and I'm glad the
section exists, but it's a bit of a
letdown if you, like me, did just 20 km
on dedicated cycling infrastructure.
Point Grey Road features culde-sacs and
other modal filters that limit car
through traffic, meaning the only cars
you see on the road are likely people
living along it. It's basically a
neighborhood greenway, and quite a
lovely one. I never felt unsafe on it,
and there were other riders out there
with me. It's just that I wanted to not
even think about cars at all on this
trip, and I did have to remain vigilant
on this section. But Point Grey Road did
a nice job of funneling me into the path
system of Jericho Beach Park, the
beginning of the last phase of our
journey, which I like to call the
beaches, as there are several of them. I
really love this concession stand at
Jericho Beach. By this point, it was
afternoon and I hadn't really eaten
anything since I left 3 hours ago, but
the menu was looking pretty darn good to
me. But I realized I was getting close
to my final destination, and I needed to
press onward. Maybe I could grab a
smokey on the way back, whatever that
is. But my journey continued onward,
only a couple more kilometers to go
along the beaches. At this point, I'm
back on the gravel from Kitalano, which
again, I don't love. But here, it sort
of underscores how far out we're getting
from the city center. There isn't really
any dense housing anymore, and it feels
really and truly suburban out here. The
only indication that we're really on the
Seaw path is the occasional bike share
docks, which almost seem out of place
this far out here. But one thing I began
to notice was the lack of geese. I
couldn't understand why they wouldn't be
on the lawn or beaches as I cycled
toward my destination. But then I saw
that I had gone so far that I had
traveled into a new habitat for a new
apex predator, the bunny rabbit. They
were everywhere in the grass there and
even assigned not to feed them.
Apparently, they were so tough they kept
the geese at bay. And after the geese, I
knew that it was best to keep my
distance and did so. Finally, I made it
to Spanish Banks Park, where the city's
website says is the official end of the
seaw wall. If I was checking my phone
more, I would have realized that this
park was quite long. I didn't though,
and I kept looking for the end of the
path, worried that somehow I'd missed
it, and I was now on a different path or
something. But nope, eventually I did
reach the end. There's no fanfare here,
just a gate, and then a diversion into a
beach with off leaf dogs. Now, let's let
pass me share my thoughts on the 28 km
journey. Okay, I think I made it to the
end. Uh, really, you can't go any
farther. There's a little path behind
me, but it's not really for bikes. Uh,
at this point though, I'm so close to
UBC, I can't imagine, uh, the city would
want to stop here. I would assume that
there's probably some sort of future
plan to connect it all the way along the
the waterfront here, but uh yeah, that
felt like 28 km. Uh I don't know if it
was exactly, but uh it was a really fun
ride. I can't believe that I started in
the heart of downtown Vancouver and now
I'm like uh four beaches away from uh uh
False Creek at this point. Um so it was
really an amazing trip. Uh well worth it
if you're in Vancouver. It's a great way
to get a good cross-section of the city.
So much fun. I'm sure voiceover Dave
will have more thoughts on it. But right
now, uh I've been on the trail here for
about I don't know three hours. Uh
that's with a lot of stopping to film.
Uh but definitely getting hungry. So I'm
going to go find some food and uh all
right, I'll give it over to voiceover
Dave. In fact, I do have more to say and
I'll say it as I bike all the way back
to the bike rental shop. I'm not going
back on the seaw wall, but instead
cutting through the city as my battery
is starting to get low and the person at
the shop said I probably can get only
about 40 km on a charge. The seaw wall
is a great example of a long-distance
bike path that can be used for bicycle
tourism. Bicycle tourism is a rapidly
growing industry as bikes continue to
have their moment postco and people are
looking for more sustainable and
authentic whatever that means forms of
tourism. The cool thing about bicycle
tourism is that it can mean a day trip
like the one I just took or a multi-day
trip, say cycling through Europe, or one
of those crazy cross-continent trips
people take. There are guided bicycle
tours, or you can just go solo.
Increasingly, rural areas are seeing
this as an economic development
strategy. Quiet rural roads can make for
great bicycle tourism locations. But I
bet these areas would get even more
tourism if they had mode separation,
like the kind you get on a good rails to
trails project, for example. And I
should say that there's just something
fundamentally great about riding your
bike long distances without worrying
about cars. Whether it's for recreation
or a commute, it's just a good time.
Vancouver SeiWall gives residents and
visitors that experience, and I can't
wait to come back and ride it again. I
also think the advent of ebikes with
their increasingly long ranges will open
up long-distance cycling to a greater
number of people. My rental bike didn't
have a huge capacity, but some are
getting 100 km or more to a charge. And
that's enough for a nice day trip on a
long-distance path. These longerdist
ebikes coupled with paths could also
mean that cities could build bicycle
highway networks of sorts to encourage
longer commutes from the suburbs. In
places with mild weather, like
Vancouver, this could be an allyear
activity. But like I said though, my
bike could only go 40 km and I was
sweating the last stretch back to
spokes. My battery indicator was on the
last bar and then that bar started
flashing just as I arrived to return it.
Having pedled the entire seaw wall, I
would absolutely recommend someone
taking the same trip. It's an amazing
way to see the city. You get to see so
many different neighborhoods. It's like
taking a transect or straight cut
through the city and experiencing
everything along that slice. The bike
rental was something like $60 for 6
hours and I really can't think of a
better use of $60 if you're visiting the
city. There's something great about
taking a long whining journey like this
just for the sake of doing it. As I was
on this Vancouver trip, I realized I was
sort of doing an urban version of a
Downey Live excursion. For those who
don't know, Mike Downey does these
incredible trips over on his channel,
like 4 days on a road train across
Australia or riding the world's longest
model train track. Right now, he's
posting this epic trip where he's taking
a friend with him on a trip from the
furthest edge of Europe all the way to
the other side of Asia. They're only
taking trains, and it's addictive to
follow along. I got to say, these guys
just bring an incredible energy, and
they're clearly having the time of their
lives. They aren't speedrunning this
trip, but instead taking time at each
major destination to soak in the
culture, which could include painting
tiles, tasting wine on a boat, eating a
rabbit in a cooking class, and strolling
through charming Italian streets. The
series is called Downey Express, and
it's a Nebula original where new
episodes are always one episode ahead on
Nebula. I highly recommend you check it
out and I highly recommend you check it
out on Nebula to see their latest
adventures as soon as the new episode
drops. That's one of my favorite things
about Nebula. You get early access to
all kinds of great content. I post my
videos on Nebula, a full video early. If
you see a video of mine posted on
YouTube, that means my next video is up
on Nebula already. At that point, people
are talking about it on my Nebula
exclusive Discord and sometimes already
posting about it on my social media.
Subscribing to Nebula means that you're
always in the loop. Downey Express is
also what we call a Nebula original, a
series funded by Nebula. They're higher
budget, more ambitious projects than
you'd find on YouTube. I have a Nebula
original series called Great Cities,
which chronicles the most important
pieces of infrastructure in the world's
greatest cities. Great Cities is
exclusive to Nebula, which means you
can't watch it anywhere else. Even just
regular old videos are better on Nebula
because they come without these ad reads
at the end. So you can watch my videos
ad free over there as well as Downey
Live, Not Just Bikes, City Nerd,
Wendover Productions, and more. All ad
free. In all, Nebula offers you, the
viewer, an ad-free experience filled
with videos produced by a curated group
of thoughtful YouTubers. And those
thoughtful creators are also publishing
big budget, high-quality, exclusive
content. You can get all this for
surprisingly affordable price. And when
you sign up at my link, nebula.tv/
citybut, you get 40% off the annual
subscription. my channel will you get a
portion of that subscription fee as long
as you stay subscribed. So, it's one of
the best ways to support me and this
channel. Nebula is also offering
lifetime memberships for people who want
to go above and beyond in their support
of my channel and the platform. I love
that we have a couple of different ways
to allow people to show their support.
So, go click on the link and start
exploring both the content and the world
thanks to Downey Express.